Guide to the Frederick Knott Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Frederick Knott papers
1923-2003
1948-2003
GEN MSS 794
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
18.7
(47 boxes) + 1 record album storage
The collection consists of material created and accumulated by Frederick Knott in the course of his activities as a playwright and screenwriter. Material includes drafts of scripts, production photographs, printed ephemera and audiovisual recordings. Writings include drafts of stage and film versions of Dial M for Murder, and photographs, contracts and other documentation of the film version directed by Alfred Hitchcock. Other material documents the writing and production of Wait Until Dark and Write Me a Murder. A small amount of student papers in Series III (Personal Papers) and writings dating from Knott's childhood document his early life.
Knott, Frederick
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from the Estate of Frederick Knott on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Access to original audiovisual recordings is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Frederick Knott, 1916-2002
Frederick Major Paull Knott, playwright and screenwriter, was born August 28, 1916 in Hankow, China to British missionary parents. He was sent to England at the age of ten for schooling, and he entered Cambridge University in 1934, where he excelled at tennis. During the Second World War, Knott served served as an artillery officer in the British army. After the war, Knott turned to writing and his first play was produced in 1952. He authored the plays Dial M for Murder and Wait Until Dark, which were enormously successful on Broadway and in London's West End in the 1950s and 1960s. He also wrote the screenplay for the film version of Dial M for Murder, which was directed by Alfred Hitchcock in 1954. Knott died in New York on December 17, 2002.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of material created and accumulated by Frederick Knott in the course of his activities as a playwright and screenwriter. Material includes drafts of scripts, production photographs, printed ephemera and audiovisual recordings. Writings include drafts of stage and film versions of Dial M for Murder, and photographs, contracts and other documentation of the film version directed by Alfred Hitchcock. Other material documents the writing and production of Wait Until Dark and Write Me a Murder. A small amount of student papers in Series III (Personal Papers) and writings dating from Knott's childhood document his early life.
Arrangement
Organized into six series: I. Correspondence, 1951-1992. II. Writings, 1927-2002. III. Personal Papers, 1923-2003. IV. Printed Material, 1941-circa 1999. V. Photographs, circa 1920-1979. VI. Audiovisual Material, 1984-2002.
Motion picture producers and directors; Dramatists, English -- 20th Century; Screenwriters; Suspense fiction; Audiovisual materials; Photographic prints; Slides (photographs); Directors; Dramatists; Screenwriters; Hitchcock, Alfred, 1899-1980; Knott, Frederick
- Correspondence, 1951-1992; Series I; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence is fragmentary and includes family correspondence as well as letters and records relating to writers' organizations to which Knott belonged.
  Correspondence files relating to specific works are filed in Series II (Writings).
  - Davis, Allan, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    Relating to "Dial M for Murder," London production
  - Knott, Ann and Margaret (including transcripts), 1958-2002 (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
  - Knott, Cyril and Margaret, 1958-1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
  - Mystery Writers of America, Inc., 1962-2002 (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
  - National Assembly of Authors and Dramatists, 1957 May (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Sherwood, James, 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Invitations and greeting cards, 1937-2002 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Unsorted correspondence, 1951-1992, undated (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
- Writings, 1927-2002; Series II; 14.22; (34 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by title. Untitled and unidentified writings are filed at the end of the series.
  Writings consist chiefly of autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, many annotated, of scripts for stage and film. Many files also include notes, correspondence, photographs, clippings, and other related papers. Of particular interest are the files relating to Dial M for Murder, which include shooting scripts for the film directed by Alfred Hitchcock, and photographs that document the production of the film.
  In addition to playscripts and screenplays, the series includes drafts of early short stories, as indicated on folder titles.
  - The Ceiling People, typescript, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - December Gold, drafts and notes, 1979, undated (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
  - Dial M for Murder
    - "Preparatory work," notes, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - "Original scribbles," notes, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
    - Synopses for Dial M for Murder and Come Down and See Me, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Script, "Original draft," typescript, 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 25-26)
    - Script, "Master copy," typescript (copy), undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Final playing version, London stage, typescript (copy), 1984 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Script, Westminster, typescript, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 29-30)
    - Rehearsal script, typescript (copy), 1966 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Script, typescript, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Script "F. Knott Master Copy," typescript, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Scripts, typescript, circa 1952 (Box 5, Folder 34-35)
    - Script, printed version (copy), undated (Box 5, Folder 36-37)
    - Scripts, printed versions, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 38-39)
    - Scripts, printed version, annotated, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 40-48)
    - Scripts, printed version, annotated, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 49-51)
    - Scripts, printed version, annotated, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 52-55)
    - Scripts, printed version, annotated, undated (Box 7, Folder 56-60)
    - Screenplay, "rough copy", undated (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - Screenplay "for Korda", undated (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - Shooting script for Hitchcock film, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 63-65)
    - "Original script" for Hitchcock film, with photographs, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 66)
    - Screenplay for Hitchcock film, signed by the cast and staff, [1953] (Box 8, Folder 67)
    - Screenplay for Hitchcock film, signed by the cast and staff, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 68)
    - Screenplay, "spare copy", 1953 (Box 9, Folder 69)
    - Script for television movie, undated (Box 9, Folder 70-71)
    - BBC script, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 72-74)
    - Script for A Perfect Murder, Time Life version, [1997] (Box 10, Folder 75-76)
    - Letters, agreements, contracts, 1948-1980, undated (Box 10, Folder 77-79)
    - Film rights, Hitchcock sketches, 1951-2002 (Box 11, Folder 80-83)
    - Contracts and sketches, 1952-1954, undated (Box 11, Folder 84-85)
    - Executed contract, Warner Bros., 1972-1974 (Box 11, Folder 86)
    - Basic film rights, 1952 (Box 11, Folder 87)
    - Photographs: Stills and production photographs, [1953] (Box 11, Folder 88)
    - Photograph of marquis (Plymouth), 1952 or 1953 (Box 11, Folder 89)
    - Television photographs, 1953 (Box 11, Folder 90)
    - Correspondence about HBO version, 1983-1984 (Box 11, Folder 91)
    - Memorabilia (copies), undated (Box 11, Folder 92)
    - Script for French adaptation, "Le crime etait presque parfait", undated (Box 12, Folder 93)
    - Playbills, posters, 1983-2002, undated (Box 12, Folder 94-95)
    - Clippings, 1952-1954 (Box 12, Folder 96)
    - Clippings, foreign languages, 1952-1955, undated (Box 12, Folder 97-99)
    - Clippings about television version, 1958 (Box 13, Folder 100)
    - Clippings for scrapbook, 1952-1954 (Box 13, Folder 101)
    - Memorabilia, 1951-1952 (Box 13, Folder 102)
    - Clippings (BBC television), 1962 (Box 13, Folder 103)
    - Clippings and reviews, 1995-1996 (Box 13, Folder 104)
    - Scrapbook, 1952-1953 (Box 14, Folder 105)
    - Set drawings, undated
  - The Face, typescript carbon, undated (Box 15, Folder 106)
  - The Honeys, by Roald Dahl
    - Clippings, 1955 (Box 15, Folder 107)
    - Notes/outline, 1955, undated (Box 15, Folder 108)
    - Script, undated (Box 15, Folder 109)
  - I Will Remember, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 15, Folder 110)
  - The Late Mr. Elvesham, by H.G. Wells, treatment by Knott, typescript, undated (Box 15, Folder 111)
  - Madame Fantasia, notes, undated (Box 15, Folder 112)
  - Man Bait, correspondence, 1951-1952 (Box 15, Folder 113)
  - The Man with the Big Feet, typescript, undated (Box 15, Folder 114)
  - Mr. Fox of Venice
    - Script for Evil of the Day, first draft, undated (Box 16, Folder 115)
    - Script for Evil of the Day, second draft, undated (Box 16, Folder 116)
    - Scripts, 1959-1963, undated (Box 16, Folder 117-122)
    - Scripts, 1959-1963, undated (Box 17, Folder 123-129)
    - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 18, Folder 130)
    - Mr. Fox's waltz, manuscript and copies, 1959, undated (Box 18, Folder 131)
    - Clippings, 1959 (Box 18, Folder 132)
    - Playbills, undated (Box 18, Folder 133)
    - Correspondence, notes, and clippings, 1955-1959, undated (Box 18, Folder 134-140)
    - Production photographs, undated (Box 18, Folder 141)
    - The Evil of the Day by Thomas Sterling, printed version, annotated, 1955 (Box 18, Folder 142)
    - "English Souvenirs", 1959, undated (Box 18, Folder 143)
    - Memorabilia, undated
  - A Murder in the Air, typescript, [1934] (Box 19, Folder 144)
  - Mystery Round Table stories, drafts, typescript and autograph manuscript, undated (Box 19, Folder 145-146)
  - Wait Until Dark
    - "Scribbles before writing," autograph manuscript, 1959-1962 (Box 19, Folder 147)
    - Notes and drafts, autograph manuscript, 1964-1966, undated (Box 19, Folder 148-150)
    - Script, "Very early draft," typescript and carbon, corrected, undated (Box 20, Folder 151-152)
    - Notes and clippings, 1962-1964 (Box 20, Folder 153)
    - Script, "Complete, uncorrected draft", undated (Box 20, Folder 154)
    - Script, "Second draft", 1966 (Box 20, Folder 155-156)
    - Script, "Third draft", 1966 (Box 21, Folder 157-160)
    - Script, "Fourth draft", 1967 (Box 21, Folder 161-162)
    - Script, "Tony Sharp Script," accompanied by correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 22, Folder 163)
    - Script, "First copyright of play as unpublished", 1964 (Box 22, Folder 164)
    - Scripts, drafts, undated (Box 22, Folder 165-167)
    - Scripts, drafts, 1967, undated (Box 23, Folder 168-173)
    - Scripts, drafts, 1967, undated (Box 24, Folder 174-178)
    - Scripts, printed versions, annotated, 1967-1992 (Box 25, Folder 179-193)
    - Scripts, printed versions, annotated, 1967-1992 (Box 26, Folder 194-195)
    - Notes, undated (Box 26, Folder 196)
    - Clippings, 1963-1965 (Box 26, Folder 197)
    - Clippings, English production, 1998, undated (Box 26, Folder 198)
    - Drafts of contract, 1965 (Box 26, Folder 199)
    - Copyright documents, 1965, 1992 (Box 26, Folder 200)
    - Contract, 1997 (Box 26, Folder 201)
    - Contract, 2002 (Box 26, Folder 202)
    - Correspondence with International Creative Management, and notes, 1967-1993 (Box 26, Folder 203)
    - Contract (copy), 1990s (Box 27, Folder 204)
    - Photographs, 1960s (Box 27, Folder 205)
    - Playbills and posters, 1954, 1967, undated (Box 27, Folder 206-209)
    - Poster for Spanish version, undated
    - Correspondence, notes and clippings, 1965-1967 (Box 27, Folder 210-213)
    - "Some material for scrapbook," correspondence and clippings, 1966-1968 (Box 28, Folder 214-215)
    - Clippings, 1966 (Box 28, Folder 216-217)
    - Copyright, financial forms, 1990s (Box 28, Folder 218)
    - Clippings, Boston and New Haven, 1965-1966, 1984 (Box 28, Folder 219)
    - Cast list and production schedule, 1965 (Box 28, Folder 220)
    - "Tarentino production," clippings, ephemera, correspondence, and casting documents, 1998 (Box 29, Folder 221-222)
  - Write Me A Murder
    - Script, "Very early draft," typescript, undated (Box 29, Folder 223)
    - Script ("King of the Castle"), notes and drafts, autograph manuscript, 1960
    - Script ("King of the Castle"), draft, typescript, undated (Box 29, Folder 224-227)
    - Script, "First and second draft for binding", undated (Box 30, Folder 228-229)
    - Scripts, "King of the Castle", undated (Box 30, Folder 230-233)
    - Scripts, "When No One Is Looking", undated (Box 31, Folder 234-237)
    - Scripts, drafts, typescript, 1961-1962, undated (Box 31, Folder 238-239)
    - Scripts, drafts, typescript, 1961-1962, undated (Box 32, Folder 240-246)
    - Scripts, drafts, typescript, 1961-1962, undated (Box 33, Folder 247-252)
    - Scripts, drafts, typescript, 1961-1962, undated (Box 34, Folder 253-254)
    - Scripts, printed versions, annotated, 1962 (Box 34, Folder 255-256)
    - "When No One Is Looking," synopsis, undated (Box 34, Folder 257)
    - Clippings, correspondence, and ephemera, 1961, undated (Box 34, Folder 258-260)
    - Posters and photographs, undated (Box 34, Folder 261)
    - Lyric Theatre poster, 1962?
    - Photograph of marquis (Lyric), 1962 (Box 35, Folder 262)
    - Clippings, correspondence, and photographs, "Souvenirs", 1959-1962 (Box 35, Folder 263-264)
    - Clippings, "Out-of-town productions", 1962, undated (Box 35, Folder 265)
    - Clippings, "New York notices", 1961 (Box 35, Folder 266)
    - Drawings and description of the "bang contraption", undated (Box 35, Folder 267)
    - Drawings for set, undated (Box 35, Folder 268)
    - Memorabilia, undated (Box 35, Folder 269-270)
    - Ephemera, "London Set", 1962 (Box 35, Folder 271)
  - Untitled and unidentified works
    - Early stories, age 12, autograph manuscript, [1928] (Box 35, Folder 272)
    - "Notes for future plays," autograph manuscript, 1949 (Box 35, Folder 273)
    - Short stories, typescript, undated (Box 35, Folder 274)
    - Unsorted notes, 1954-1966, undated (Box 36, Folder 275-284)
- Personal Papers, 1923-2003; Series III; 1.46; (4 boxes)
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  Personal papers consist of financial papers, official documents, transcripts of interviews, and fragmentary documentation of Frederick Knott's early life, including photographs and educational records.
  - Copyright papers, 1966-2003 (Box 37, Folder 285-286)
  - Release settlement, 1985 (Box 37, Folder 287)
  - Financial papers, 1923-2001 (Box 37, Folder 288-291)
  - Financial papers, 1923-2001 (Box 38, Folder 292-295)
  - Diary, 1948-1952 (Box 38, Folder 296)
  - Cambridge entrance essays, 1934, undated (Box 38, Folder 297)
  - "Frederick Knott's comments to son Anthony", 1958-1960 (Box 38, Folder 298)
  - "Lessons Frederick Knott learned", 1959 (Box 38, Folder 299)
  - Tennis scrapbook, 1935-1939 (Box 39, Folder 300)
  - Tennis tour book, 1937 (Box 39, Folder 301)
  - Emigration papers, 1939-1946 (Box 39, Folder 302)
  - Discussion with agent, transcript, undated (Box 39, Folder 303)
  - "AFK Allen Stevenson's report", 1965-1967 (Box 39, Folder 304)
  - Estate planning, 1965-1967 (Box 39, Folder 305)
  - Certificate of Naturalization, 1996 (Box 39, Folder 306)
  - Marriage license, 1953 (Box 39, Folder 307)
  - References for immigration to the U.S., 1953 (Box 39, Folder 308)
  - Birth registration of Anthony Frederick Knott, 1960 (Box 39, Folder 309)
  - Diplomas, 1938-1945 (Box 39, Folder 310)
  - Unsorted papers, 1961-1996 (Box 40, Folder 311-316)
    Includes clippings, correspondence, and personal papers
- Printed Material, 1941-circa 1999; Series IV; 0.42; (1 box)
  The series consists chiefly of unsorted playbills and clippings, and also includes Frederick Knott's annotated copy of the Little Oxford Dictionary.
  - Little Oxford Dictionary, 1941 (Box 41, Folder 317)
  - Playbills, 1947-1996, undated (Box 41, Folder 318-323)
  - Unsorted clippings, 1980s-1990s (Box 41, Folder 324-325)
- Photographs, circa 1920-1979; Series V; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  Organized into two subseries: Prints and Slides.
  Photographs depict Frederick Knott's childhood in China and early adulthood in England, and several stage and film productions, including Alfred Hitchcock's 1954 film Dial M for Murder.
  Photographs relating to a particular work can also be found in Series II.
  - Prints
    - Childhood in China, circa 1920 (Box 42, Folder 326)
    - Photograph album: England, 1930s (Box 42, Folder 327)
    - Frederick Knott, including portraits, military service and wedding, 1930s-1950s (Box 42, Folder 328)
    - India, 1940s (Box 42, Folder 329)
    - Dial M for Murder, various film and stage versions, production photographs, 1950s (Box 42, Folder 330)
    - Unidentified production photographs, 1950s (Box 42, Folder 331)
    - Unidentified production photographs, 1952 (Box 42, Folder 332)
    - Grace Kelly, and Alfred Hitchcock's house, 1953? (Box 42, Folder 333-334)
    - Dial M for Murder, film version, production photographs, 1953 (Box 42, Folder 335)
    - Dial M for Murder, set, Reykjavik, 1955 (Box 42, Folder 336)
    - Robert Morley head shot, circa 1960 (Box 42, Folder 337)
    - Snapshot: a family in Marion, Indiana, 1960 (Box 42, Folder 338)
    - Mr. Fox stills, circa 1960 (Box 42, Folder 339)
    - Anthony Knott in front of a poster for Write Me A Murder, circa 1965 (Box 42, Folder 340)
  - Slides
    - Cambridge, undated (Box 43, Folder 341)
    - A and A Conrad/Hitchcock and Co., 1953 (Box 43, Folder 342)
    - Alfred Hitchcock's house, slides, 1953? (Box 43, Folder 343-344)
    - Dial M for Murder, film version, stereo slides, 1953 (Box 43, Folder 345-347)
    - Play posters by Day, 1979 (Box 43, Folder 348)
    - Wait Until Dark Theatres (exteriors): Shubert, Strand, Downing, etc., 1966 (Box 43, Folder 349)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 43, Folder 350-354)
    - Stereo slide viewer, undated (Box 43, Folder 355)
- Audiovisual Material, 1984-2002; Series VI; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Boxes 44-45 and 48 (audiovisual material): Resticted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Audiovisual material documents stage and television productions of Dial M for Murder and Wait Until Dark, and interviews with Frederick Knott.
  - "On Drinking," with transcript, copy, undated; 1; 00:31:31; The program is distorted at times. High background noise can be heard on the tape. The program ends abruptly. (Box 44, Item barcode 39002091397977)
    Interview with son, Anthony.
  - History of "Dial M for Murder," with transcript, undated; 1; 00:31:26; The program is distorted at times. High background noise can be heard on the tape. Silence recorded from 05:19-05:26. (Box 44, Item barcode 39002091397985)
    Contents reveal why he wrote the play. Interview by his son, Anthony.
  - Write Me a Murder, (1 of 2 audiocassettes), undated; 1; 01:01:46; Program is distorted at times. (Box 45, Item barcode 39002091397910)
  - Write Me a Murder, (2 of 2 audiocassettes), undated; 1; 00:30:49; The program is distorted at times. High background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 45, Item barcode 39002091397928)
  - Kaye Brown and Frederick Knott discussing film play, When No One is Looking, funeral scene, undated; 1; 00:35:46; The program is distorted at times. High background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 45, Item barcode 39002091397944)
  - Write Me a Murder, Frederick Knott with Kay Brown, original, undated; 1; 00:26:07; High background noise can be heard on the tape. The program ends abruptly. (Box 45, Item barcode 39002091397951)
  - "Freddie talking to Anthony", undated; 1; 00:32:02; A warble in the audio can be heard at the end of the tape. (Box 45, Item barcode 39002091397969)
  - Freddie Knott. Wait Until Dark, Front Row, BBC Radio 4, 2003; 1; 00:08:18; The program is distorted at times. High background noise can be heard on the tape. The program ends abruptly. (Box 45, Item barcode 39002091397936)
    Background profile of Frederick Knott. Presented by Mark Lawson.
  - Dial M for Murder, Hitchcock version, 1984 September 3; GENMSS794_0001; 1; 01:07:48 (Box 45, Item barcode 39002102370732)
    This tape begins sometime into the movie.
  - Dial M for Murder, Hitchcock version, #2, Lesgate version, 18 minutes, 1996 January 5; GENMSS794_0002; 1; 01:46:25 (Box 45, Item barcode 39002102370740)
  - Wait Until Dark, off-Broadway theatre, 1985 November 11; GENMSS794_0003; 1; 01:58:56 (Box 45, Item barcode 39002102370757)
  - Wait Until Dark, The Doug Brode Review Live, Syracuse Stage, Guests: Arthur Storch, Frederick Knott, 1989 April 5; GENMSS794_0004; 1; 01:00:42 (Box 45, Item barcode 39002102370765)
  - Wait Until Dark, Channel 11, Bob Haskins, Heart Condition, 1997 August 16; GENMSS794_0005; 1; 01:41:47 (Box 45, Item barcode 39002102370773)
  - Perfect Murder, 2002 October 19; GENMSS794_0006; 1; 01:35:01 (Box 45, Item barcode 39002102370781)
  - Wait Until Dark, by Garry Blake, 1966; 1 phonograph record (Box 48 (Record album storage), Folder 380)
- Oversize Material, 0.5; (2 boxes)
  - Dial M For Murder, posters (Series II), undated (Box 46, Folder 370)
  - Dial M For Murder, clippings (Series II), 1952-1953 (Box 46, Folder 371)
  - Wait Until Dark, drafts (Series II), undated (Box 46, Folder 371a)
  - Wait Until Dark, poster for Spanish version (Series II), undated (Box 46, Folder 372)
  - Write Me a Murder, Lyric Theatre poster (Series II), 1962? (Box 46, Folder 373)
  - December Gold, drafts (Series II), 1979, undated (Box 47, Folder 374)
  - Dial M For Murder, set drawings (Series II), undated (Box 47, Folder 374a)
  - Mr. Fox of Venice, memorabilia (Series II), undated (Box 47, Folder 375)
  - Write Me a Murder ("King of the Castle"), draft, autograph manuscript (Series II), 1960 (Box 47, Folder 376-377)
  - Write Me a Murder, drawings for set (Series II), undated (Box 47, Folder 378)
  - Diplomas (Series III), 1938 (Box 47, Folder 379)